well
好吧，
the short talk is this
简短的谈话是这样的，
I did a lot of math
我做了很多数学工作，
I made a lot of money
我赚了很多钱
and I gave almost all of it away
，我几乎把所有的钱都捐了出去，
that's the story of my life now
这就是我现在的生活故事，
it's a good story but it's short
这是一个好故事，但它很短，
so
所以
when I was a little boy
当我还是个小男孩时，
I uh I liked math in the sense that I
我呃我 喜欢数学是因为
like to when I was three or four or
我三四岁的时候
something like that double the numbers
喜欢把数字加倍
to 4 8 16 32 episode
到 4 8 16 32 集
Etc
等等
I got up to a thousand and twenty four
我达到了一千二十四，
and I said enough of that but uh but I I
我说得够多了但是呃但是我
like doubling numbers
喜欢加倍 数字
and uh
，呃，
when I was a little boy also
当我还是个小男孩的时候，
I was in my father's my father was
我也在我父亲的车里，我父亲
driving me and he said he has to
开车送我，他说他必须
go to a gas station and get gasoline I
去加油站买汽油，我
said why do you need to get gasoline he
说你为什么需要汽油，他
says well
说好吧，
a car needs gasoline I said but you
汽车需要汽油 我说过，但你
shouldn't need to have to get gasoline
不应该需要得到汽油，
you could just use half of what you now
你可以只使用你现在
have and then half of that and half of
拥有的一半，然后一半，
that and half of that and you'll never
一半，一半，如果没有所谓的芝诺悖论，你永远
run out of gas
不会用完汽油
without what's called Zeno's Paradox but
但是
uh
呃
because it didn't occur to me that we
因为我没有想到我们也
wouldn't get very far either but uh
不会走得太远但是呃就
there there it was
在那里
but I did always always like math and uh
但我总是喜欢数学而且呃
I went to MIT
我去了麻省理工学院
and uh
而且呃
I took a graduate course right in my
我在大一的时候就修了研究生课程
which uh was puzzling to me it was
这让我感到困惑，它是
abstract algebra
抽象代数，
but during this
但在今年
summer I figured it all out I got a book
夏天，我把它全部弄清楚了，我得到了一本书，
I figured it all out and and then took a
我把它全部弄清楚了，然后在麻省理工学院选修了
lot of math courses
很多数学课程，
um
嗯，
and uh
呃，
well the field that I really liked
我真正喜欢的领域
was called differential geometry
是 称为微分几何
how many of you have ever heard of
你们中有多少人听说过微分几何
okay
好吧，
the old folks know about different
老人们都知道不同的
geometry well differential geometry is a
几何学 微分几何是
study of curved spaces in in many
对多维弯曲空间的研究，
with typically with a metric on it so
通常带有一个度量，这样
you can see how far apart any two points
您就可以看到任意两个 要点
would would be
是，
and uh I really like that field
呃，我真的很喜欢这个领域，嗯，
um
嗯，
I went to Berkeley
我去了伯克利，
I forgot my well I I graduated MIT in
我忘记了，我三年后从麻省理工学院毕业，
three years so I stayed as a graduate
所以我作为研究生呆了
for a year
一年，
and then they told me
然后他们告诉我
you should go to Berkeley and I said why
你应该去伯克利，我 说为什么
why should I go to Berkeley they said
为什么我应该去伯克利他们说
well the great man in your field
好吧，微分几何领域的伟人，
a man named chern
一个叫陈的人
is just going to Berkeley
即将去伯克利
and you should work under churn
，你应该在搅动下工作，
so I said okay so I went out to Berkeley
所以我说好吧，所以我去了伯克利，
regrettably uh churn
遗憾的是呃搅动
was taking a sabbatical leave that year
正在接受 那年休假，
and so he wasn't there so I worked with
所以他不在那儿，所以我和
someone else and that that worked out
其他人一起工作，结果
fine
很好，
uh it was interesting
呃，很有趣，
uh working with this guy
呃，和这个人一起工作，
I came up with a little theorem and I
我想出了一个小定理，我
showed it to him
给他看了，
and he said oh that's a nice little
他说哦，那就是 一个很好的小
theorem
定理，
it puts in mind
它提出了
an open question which I won't
一个悬而未决的问题，我不会
really describe to you
真正向你描述这个问题，
but uh but don't work on that question I
但是呃，但不要解决这个问题我
said why he said because it's too tough
说为什么他说因为这太难了这个这个
this this one worked on it and tried and
研究并尝试了
that one worked on it and tried
那个 努力并尝试得
well of course that just sort of got me
很好，当然这让我继续
going and uh I said okay but I I'm going
前进，呃我说好吧，但我会
to work in this problem and uh well uh
解决这个问题，呃好吧呃
I did and I solved the problem
我做到了，我解决了这个问题，
and I was very pleased with myself
我对自己非常满意
and uh
呃
went back to teach at MIT and Harvard
回到麻省理工学院和哈佛大学任教，
but for reasons which I won't go into
但由于一些我不会谈论的原因
I uh I needed money
我呃我需要钱
and I had borrowed money to invest in a
，我和我的一些朋友借了钱投资一家
company with some friends of mine
公司，
and I need needed to pay it back
我需要偿还它，
but there was a place in Princeton
但有 普林斯顿的一个地方
called The Institute for defense
叫做国防分析研究所，
which was a highly
这是一个高度
classified place
机密的地方，
under the Aegis of the government the
受政府国防部的支持，
defense department and what we're
我们
supposed to do
应该做的
is uh break Russian codes
是呃破解俄罗斯密码，
well that was an interesting challenge
这是一个有趣的挑战
uh
呃
I like the work
我喜欢
they told us you could do your own
他们的工作 告诉我们你可以用一半的时间做你自己的
mathematics up to half your time the
数学，
other half you had to do you know this
另一半你必须做你知道这个
cold cracking business
冷裂业务，
and well uh
嗯，
during that period
在那段时间
I was very interested in an area of
我对一个叫做最小曲面的数学领域非常感兴趣，
any of you know what a minimal surface
你们有人知道吗？ 最小表面
well someone must know what a minimal
很好，有人必须知道什么
surface is okay so a minimal surface is
是最小表面，所以最小表面是
a surface of minimal area with respect
相对于其边界具有最小面积的表面，
so imagine taking a wire frame just a
所以想象一下，将一个线框只是一个
closed frame
封闭的框架，
dip it in
将其
so in in so soap suds
浸入肥皂水中
and then take it out
，然后 把它拿出来，
and there'll be a film
就会有一个薄膜，
that is bounded by this thing and that
它被这个东西和那个
film that soap film
薄膜所包围，肥皂薄膜的
has less an area than any other surface
面积比任何其他
with that boundary so that's a minimal
有这个边界的表面都要小，所以这是一个最小的，
that's a minimal surface and uh
这是一个最小的表面，呃，
the first Fields Prize winner
第一个菲尔兹奖获得者
uh back in maybe 1905
呃回来 也许在 1905 年，他
had proved that any such boundary
已经证明，任何这样的边界
would have
都会有
a minimal surface just one and it would
一个最小的表面，只有一个，而且它
be smooth it wouldn't have any points or
是光滑的，不会有任何点或
anything like that it would just be a
类似的东西，它只是一个
nice smooth surface
很好的光滑表面，
and as I said he won the fields medal
正如我所说，他赢得了菲尔兹奖
for that
那个
and um so I got interested in that area
，嗯，所以当我在国防分析研究所的时候，我对这个领域产生了兴趣，
so in my spare time which was
所以在我的业余时间里，
quite a lot I worked on that problem
我花了很多时间研究这个问题，
because in higher dimensions
因为在更高的维度上，
it was an open was an open problem
这是一个开放的问题，
someone had done it in one dimension
有人 已经在更高的一维中完成了，
uh so that would be uh a a
所以这将是一个
in four-dimensional space
在四维空间中具有二维边界的三维表面，
and uh well uh but that's where it
嗯，嗯，但是这就是它停止的地方，
so I worked in that problem in higher
所以我在更高的维度中解决了这个问题，
dimensions and
并且
was uh lucky enough
是呃 很幸运
to solve the problem
能够
through ambient Dimension seven
通过环境第七维解决问题，
but in dimension eight
但在第八维
my proof didn't work
我的证明不起作用
and uh and I constructed what I thought
，呃，我构造了我认为
was a counter example a counter example
是一个反例的东西，反例
was something that uh
是呃
you you you think you have a
你你你认为你有一个
you've proved the theorem but someone
你已经证明的东西 定理，但有人
comes along with an example that shows
提出了一个例子，表明
you didn't prove that theorem because
你没有证明该定理，因为
this is a counter example so uh I found
这是一个反例，所以呃，我发现了
what I thought was a counter example I
我认为是反例的东西，我
couldn't prove it
无法证明它，
but a couple years and I the paper got
但几年后，我的论文得到了
published it was
发表了，这
was a pretty good paper actually
实际上是一篇相当不错的论文
and um
，嗯，
but a few years later
但是几年后，
a couple of mathematicians one of whom
几位数学家，其中一个
was named bombieri
叫邦比耶里，
and uh showed that my counter example
呃表明我的反例
was really a counter example so that
确实是一个反例，所以
well uh at a certain point
在某个时刻完全解决了这个问题呃
I came to
我来到
Stony Brook University I was 30 years
石溪大学，当时我 30 岁，
to be the chair
担任
of their math department
他们数学系的系主任，
which was not a very strong Department
那不是一个很强的系
and I was pretty young to be the
，担任系主任我还很年轻，
chairman but I thought it would be fun
但我认为这会很有趣，
and I had a lot of money to work with
而且我有很多钱可以做。 一起工作，
because
因为
the governor at the time was a guy named
当时的州长是一个叫
Rockefeller now I think everyone has
洛克菲勒的人，现在我想每个人都
probably heard of the name Rockefeller
可能听说过洛克菲勒这个名字，
but has anyone not heard of the name
但有谁没有听说过洛克菲勒这个名字，
okay most of you have heard of
好吧，你们大多数人都听说过
Rockefeller Rockefeller love the State
洛克菲勒洛克菲勒喜欢州立
University and was pouring money on it
大学并且正在投入金钱
so I had a lot of money to work with
所以我有很多钱可以合作
and uh
，呃
hired some terrific people so
雇佣了一些很棒的人，
high as I'm terrific people
因为我是很棒的人，
but at the same time in that time frame
但同时在那个时间范围内，
I started to get interested in another
我开始对
area of math
数学的另一个领域感兴趣，
and uh
呃
I worked on that area
我致力于 那个区域
and came up with something really quite
并想出了一些非常
beautiful
漂亮的
three dimensions it was a function I
三维它是一个功能我
can't really describe it but it
无法真正描述它但
it lived in three dimensions closed
它生活在三维封闭的
three-dimensional
三维
spaces
空间中
and I
我
was quite pleased
很高兴
I showed it to churn
我展示了它来搅动
I I say I showed it I we I centered by
我我说我展示了它 我以邮件为中心，
the mail because her nose days there was
因为她的鼻子天
no email
没有电子邮件
and chern said well you've done this in
，陈说，好吧，你已经在三个维度上做到了这一点，
but it should work in all dimensions
但它应该在所有维度上都有效，
I was very dubious but I said okay let's
我很怀疑，但我说好吧，让我们
work together and see
一起努力看看，
and he was right
他是 是的，
it would work in all dimensions
它适用于所有维度
and I was very pleased we published the
，我很高兴我们发表了这篇
paper
论文
and about five years later
，大约五年后，
a physicist
一位
named Whitten
名叫惠滕的物理学家
saw this paper and thought and he was
看到了这篇论文并认为他是
right it could apply to physics
对的，它可以应用于物理学，
and then some other physicists saw how
然后其他一些物理学家看到了
it could apply to physics
它如何应用于物理学 物理
I didn't know any physics at all
我根本不知道任何物理
churn might have known something but it
搅恩可能知道一些东西，但
never occurred to him that would apply
他从来没有想到这会适用
to physics
于物理，
and remarkably so you never know where
而且值得注意的是，所以你永远不知道
something will go
某些东西会去哪里，
you think you're doing math and you're
你认为你在做数学，但
actually doing physics maybe or whatever
实际上你在做物理 也许或者
so today
无论如何，今天
that is
这被
called churn Simon's Theory
称为搅动西蒙理论，
on average every day
平均每天有
four papers in physics
四篇物理学论文
reference this
引用这种
churn Simon's Theory
搅动西蒙理论，
so I can't take any credit for it at all
所以我根本不能把它归功于它，
but but there it was and of course
但它确实是这样的。 当然
I'm quite pleased about it but I can't
我对此很高兴，但我不能
say that oh I I invented this for
说哦，我为物理学发明了这个，
shortly after that
不久之后
I started to get interested
我开始
in the world of Investments
对投资世界产生兴趣，
I had come into
我投入了
a very small amount of money but it was
很少的钱，但这
enough to start investing
足以 开始投资
and one thing led to another
，一件事导致另一件事
I started hiring people
我开始雇用人员
and we made what was called a hedge fund
，我们创建了所谓的对冲基金，
and it was
它
remarkably successful
非常成功，
it's still going I'm not with it anymore
它仍在继续我不再参与它了，
but I made
但我
from this from this hedge fund
从这个对冲基金中赚了很多钱
now my lovely wife Marilyn
现在我可爱的妻子玛丽莲
said let's give some of it away
说让我们捐出一些，
so I said okay fine so we gave some
所以我说好吧，所以我们捐了一些
charity
慈善事业，
and then she said well why don't we
然后她说好吧，我们为什么不
start a foundation
建立一个基金会
and uh okay starting Foundation she
，呃，好吧，开始基金会，她
started a foundation
建立了一个基金会，
I put money into it
我投入了钱
the good thing about putting money into
把钱投入
a foundation is you can give the money
基金会的好处是你可以把钱捐出
away you've got the tax advantage but it
去，你有税收优惠，但它
doesn't have to be spent immediately so
不必立即花掉，所以
you can put money into the foundation
你可以把钱投入基金会，
and say well we'll see what we want to
然后说好吧，我们会看到我们想要的
do with it tomorrow or next year or
明天或明年或
whatever
其他任何事情，
but it grew and grew
但它不断增长，不断
and grew
增长，
so uh
所以今天哦，
oh well
好吧，
we decided to focus on science
我们决定专注于科学，
with our uh Foundation
我们的呃基金会
focus on science
专注于科学，
uh ninety percent of it should be
呃，百分之九十应该是
science 8 60 of that should be basic
科学，其中 60% 应该是科学 基础
science
科学，
and 30 of that could be translational
其中 30 个可能是转化
and 10 could be education and Outreach
，10 个可能是教育和外展
and things like that
之类的，
so today uh
所以今天呃，
that Foundation is
基金会
extremely large
非常大，
and uh so most of the money that I made
呃，所以我赚的大部分钱都
was put into the foundation
投入了基金会，
so I'm not so rich as I was before but
所以我不这么认为 我和以前一样富有，但是
uh Rich enough
呃，足够富有，
and we had this wonderful Foundation
我们有这个很棒的基金会，
and uh
呃，
running it most of the time was my
大部分时间都是我
wonderful wife
很棒的妻子在运营，有
any questions
任何问题，
no questions
没有问题，
yeah Yuri is in the foundation he just
是的，尤里在基金会里，他刚刚
talked
说过，
uh
呃，
that's a very good question
这是一个很好的问题，
I could go into that but it's a long
我可以讨论一下 但这是一个很长的
story so so I won't
故事，所以我不会提出
any other questions
任何其他问题，
okay good luck to all of you
祝大家好运
[Applause]
[鼓掌]